<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd at the cathedral church of St.Paul's on May 29, 1699, before the right honourable the Lord Mayor, aldermen, and citizens</title>
            <author>Morer, Thomas, 1651-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51355</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2723</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43468</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">27667219</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 27667219</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110173</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51355)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110173)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1730:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd at the cathedral church of St.Paul's on May 29, 1699, before the right honourable the Lord Mayor, aldermen, and citizens</title>
                  <author>Morer, Thomas, 1651-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for James Bonwicke ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXCIX [1699]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. 27.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah I, 26 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110173:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd at the Cathedral Church OF St. PAUL's, On May 29. 1699: BEFORE The Right Honourable the Lord Mayor, ALDERMEN AND CITIZENS.</p>
            <p>By THO. MORER, Rector of St. Anne, &amp;c. Alderſgate.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for James Bonwicke, at the Hat and Star in St. Paul's Church-yard, MDCXCIX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:110173:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:110173:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Iſaiah 1.26.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And I will reſtore thy Judges as at the firſt, and thy Counſellors as at the beginning.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>AS the great Work of this Holy Pen-man is Prophecy, ſo for the moſt part it is about Spiritual Things; and his main Deſign is to ſpeak of the long-deſired Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution and <hi>Reſtauration</hi> of the Church under the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Meſſias.</p>
            <p>And this Subject he immediately enters upon in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the next Chapter, <hi>Ver.</hi> 2, 3, 4. wherein he ſets before us the Glories and Advantages of that Conſtitution; the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Conflux of moſt Nations to this New Temple; the Willingneſs of the People to learn and practiſe the Duties of Religion, and readineſs to invite their Neighbours to do ſo too; together with the Happineſs attending it, ſignified by the Peace, good Diſpoſition, and ſweet Temper, among ſuch Profeſſors, whoſe Principles would direct them to lay aſide all Animoſities, and not ſuffer them to War and quarrel with one another. And tho' now under the Eſtate of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, to which the Prophecy had an Eye, there is not that Univerſal Silence of the Sword, and other Arms, as might be expected, and was at that time when the Author of it was born, <hi>The Prince of Peace;</hi> yet this is owing to Humane Frailty, and the violent Paſſions of Men, which tho' in Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Goſpel, we all renounce at our Baptiſm, yet they generally over-rule, and we ſubmit to 'em. This, I ſay, is the great Work of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> the Glory and Extent of the Empire and Religion of Meſſias, in oppoſition to the Jews, who were confined within narrow Bounds, and whoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition was for the moſt part Military and Unhappy, becauſe of the frequent Wars they were forced to ingage in for the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:110173:3"/>Defence of their Worſhip, and to ſecure Conſcience againſt the Inſults of the Infidels.</p>
            <p>Yet it is evident, according to the way of Holy Writ, (wherein there are many Intermixtures of Religious and Worldly Matters) that he inſiſts on a nearer Subject in this Chapter, and directs his Diſcourſe to the Jews with reſpect to their Civil Capacity, as they made up a <hi>State</hi> or <hi>Nation,</hi> and as ſuch to be puniſhed or proſpered in a way ſuitable to their Polity; a Way that concerns only this World, to which all theſe Appointments or Governments are limited, tho' both Governours and Governed are apart to make ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Account hereafter, and Perſonally Anſwer for their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Actions or Counſels.</p>
            <p>Here then in the firſt place he charges them, as a <hi>Nation,</hi> with many Sins of frightful Gomplexion, <hi>Injuſtice, Violence,</hi> and <hi>Rebellion, Ver.</hi> 4.21, 22, 23. The Ground of all which was a real Disbelief of what they profeſs'd; and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their fair Appearance and Pretenſions of Holineſs, yet plainly they diſſembled in what they ſaid and did. They uſed Religion only for Secular Ends, and put on this Sacred Veil to no other purpoſe then to cover their Vices. They faſted, but it was for <hi>Strife</hi> and <hi>Debate,</hi> and to <hi>ſmile with the Fist of Wickedneſs.</hi> They offer'd <hi>Incenſe,</hi> but it was <hi>Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.
<note place="margin">Ver. 14.</note> They ſpread forth their Hands, but Hands full of Blood.</hi> They pray'd to God, but like them in the Poet, to patronize their Villanies; And, as our Lord ſpeaks of the Phariſees, at the ſame time they <hi>devoured Widows Houſes, and for a ſhew made Long Prayers.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 20.47.</note> All which proves, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they believed no God at all; or, which is no leſs A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſm, denied him to be what He is, <hi>All-knowing, Righteous</hi> and <hi>Pure;</hi> Attributes, which being admitted, would quickly put a ſtop to all theſe Religious Cheats. In a word, their Claim to the True Religion did but aggravate their Wilful Abuſe of it, and their Hypocriſie ripen'd both their Sins and their Ruine; two things that commonly go together: And therefore, as in <hi>Ver.</hi> 7. they had experience of this a little before, when <hi>their Country was deſolate, and their Cities burnt with fire</hi>—
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:110173:3"/>meaning the Deſtruction wrought by the <hi>Syrians</hi> in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding Reign. So we ſind another Calamity threaten'd, <hi>V.</hi> 24. <hi>Therefore ſaith the Lord, the Lord of Hoſts, the mighty one of Iſrael, Ah, I will eaſe me of my Adverſaries, and avenge me of mine Enemies.</hi> Which was made good in the Reign after by the Oppreſſions they groaned under, when the Princes of <hi>Babylon</hi> became their Maſters.</p>
            <p>However <hi>God in Judgment remembred Mercy.</hi> And tho' their Sins called for this Miſery, and that their Provocations were ſo great, as to force him to afflict them with the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> Bondage; yet his Compaſſion was alſo great, and this ſad Meſſage by the Prophet ſhall be cloſe follow'd with a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of Comfort, eſpecially to the few Righteous among them, who, tho' involv'd in the general Diſtreſs of their Country, as making all, both Good and Bad, one Civil Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, yet they ſhould be uſed only as Gold and Silver, which is not conſumed, but purified in the Fire; as this Captivity ſhould make them better, and be employ'd as a means to cleanſe them of their Pollutions, or rather rid them of thoſe wicked Men, whoſe Sins brought that Vengeance on the Nation. And this is what was intended by thoſe Figurative Expreſſions in the Verſe before,
<note place="margin">Ver. 25.</note> 
               <hi>And I will turn my hand upon thee, and purely purge away thy Droſs, and take away all thy Tin.</hi> Which being done, then comes in the Deliverance, the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of my Text, <hi>And I will reſtore,</hi> &amp;c. which was effected by <hi>Zerubbabel,</hi> who recovered the City, and rebuilt the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>For the better underſtanding of the Prophet, 'tis neceſſary to do Two things.</p>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>Examine what</hi> this Ancient Conſtitution was he refers to.</p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>Wherein</hi> the Happineſs conſiſts in being reſtored to that Conſtitution.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I will reſtore thy Judges as at the firſt, and thy Counſellors as at the beginning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Let us examine what this Ancient <hi>Conſtitution</hi> was the Prophet points to, or the means to make 'em happy. And
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:110173:4"/>in order to this, it will lie upon us to conſider a little the Importance or Signification of thoſe Two Terms, <hi>Judges</hi> and <hi>Counſellors,</hi> the clearing of which will be ſerviceable to us.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. So the Septuagint. The firſt of which properly means <hi>one</hi> able to <hi>diſcern</hi> and <hi>diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh;</hi> who knows what is good and bad, right and wrong, and the like; and hath by Nature, Study, or long Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſo much Skill and Judgment, that when any Point is laid before him, he can remove the Perplexities, or matter of Doubts and Diſputes which ariſe between contending Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and ſhew which ſide it is that deſerves the Preference. And this being the requiſite Qualification of him who at any time is appointed to end Controverſies between Man and Man, he that hath this Truſt is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>Judge,</hi> that his Name might remember him of the Caution and <hi>Diſcretion</hi> he is to uſe in all theſe Caſes.</p>
            <p>But here 'tis conſtrued not ſo much a Word of Capacity, as of Pre-eminence and Power: And tho' the Power ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes this Capacity, (and where it is otherwiſe, they are in a very miſerable Circumſtance who are ſubject to that Power) yet we are now to lay aſide the Etymology and Grammar of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and take it as an <hi>Order,</hi> and not a <hi>Faculty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being then reſtrained to the Government of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to whom the Prophet ſpeaks, it appears from <hi>Joſephus,</hi> that all the Princes and Rulers of that People, from the Death of <hi>Joſhua</hi> to the Election of K.
<note place="margin">Antio. l. 6. c. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Saul,</hi> had this Name. <hi>All this time,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>hath been called the time of the Judges.</hi> So the Book which contains the Hiſtory of their Actions, is En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titled <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as in the Hebrew <hi>Shophetim.</hi> And in the Account of the ſeveral Reigns therein recorded, it is ſaid that ſuch a one <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Judged Iſrael at that time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But we muſt go a little higher than this; for we find that even <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf had the ſame Stile in that Oration St. <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen</hi> made the <hi>Jews</hi> juſt before his Death, where, reciting the Paſſage in which <hi>Moſes</hi> endeavoured to reconcile two of his Brethren, one of whom ill requited him for his Pains, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding peeviſhly, Who made him a Judge and a Ruler over them? <hi>This very Moſes,</hi> ſaith the Martyr, <hi>whom they refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:110173:4"/>ſaying, Who made thee a Ruler and a Judge, the ſame did God ſend to be a Ruler,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Acts</hi> 7.35.— 'Tis true, the Holy Man, or at leaſt St. <hi>Luke</hi> for him, uſes another Greek word, and calls him <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which in ſound varies, but hath the ſame ſignification, and both are tranſlated <hi>Judge.</hi> And all the difference is, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſeems of larger extent, and intends him a Perſon with ability to <hi>diſcern</hi> without deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining the Subject; whereas the latter word as a Species, is conſined to Legal Cauſes about Property or Criminal Actions. Tho' after all, there may be no more than a gradation in the Terms, the one to hear and examine the Suit, and the other to end it by Sentence. The firſt beſpeaks his <hi>Skill,</hi> the laſt his <hi>Integrity.</hi> And as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> makes him <hi>a Judge,</hi> ſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſuppoſes him <hi>Righteous,</hi> and that he will take ſpecial care to execute Juſtice without Prejudice, Partiality or Favour, as Law and Conſcience ſhall direct him. However both the words center in the Supreme Magiſtrate: And altho' by Dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation or Commiſſion the Truſt is repoſed in ſome of the Subjects whoſe capacities will bear it, yet originally the Power is lodged in the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as St. <hi>Stephen</hi> explains it, and the word denotes the Sovereign Prince or Ruler, by whatever name we diſtinguiſh him, ſuch as <hi>Moſes, Joſhua,</hi> and their followers the Judges were who had Kingly Authority,
<note place="margin">Judges 17.6.</note> and ſometimes the name, and as other Monarchs under God, governed the Children of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> And to theſe the Text refers, as being the firſt to whom the Title of <hi>Judges</hi> was given.</p>
            <p>Long before this, indeed, the Patriarchs were as Abſolute as any Emperour after them. They were Kings, Prieſts and Judges: They had Life and Death in their hands: They made War and Peace as they ſaw good; and acted Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently, or without being awed by any humane Power above their own. And of this we have a pregnant Inſtance in <hi>Abraham,</hi> who was going to Sacrifice his Son without any open Reaſon, but that of his Will. He alſo armed his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and fought and beat the four Kings who had taken his Kinſman Priſoner, yet his Army conſiſted of no more than Three hundred and eighteen Men: which, as it ſhews
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:110173:5"/>himſelf to be no Mighty Potentate, yet beating his Enemies with theſe, it proves the other four Princes weaker than He, who notwithſtanding are called Kings and they had routed five other Kings before. Plainly in thoſe days, their Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions were ſmall. The Patriarchs had no more Subjects than Servants and Children: And had all the Heads of Families been as they were, ſo Righteous, ſo void of Ambition, ſo little Covetous, ſo free from Revenge, and the like; thoſe ſuppoſed Combinations, or cloſing of leſſer Familes to oppoſe the greater, and the final Election of one among them to keep Peace among the whole, and give a timely Check to any aſpiring Spirit, who had otherwiſe grown too big for the Intereſt and Safety of his Neighbours; this Politic Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I ſay, had been kept out of doors, and we had wanted no Authority but that of Fatherhood to govern us. But Pride and Avarice, Violence and Licentiouſneſs in ſome, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting more Elbow-room than others were willing to give 'em; this fright'ned former Ages into the refuge of Aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Covenants, Laws and Rulers; by the help of which, the feebleſt Arm might be able to wreſtle with the ſtrongeſt, the meaneſt ſort to cope with the greater, and every Man and Woman either protected or relieved upon the Encroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of theſe Intruders, who elſe were ready to moleſt them.</p>
            <p>Where the True Religion had no Influence, the Neceſſity was too viſible to engage Men to theſe Combinational Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. And the Reaſon at laſt reached, not only Private Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, but the Governments alſo themſelves into which they were united; one State being forward enough to devour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, as the particular Houſes, Clans and Tribes had at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted before. Which conſtrained even them to part with their own Power, and by conſent to intruſt it with one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Sovereign, to be ſecured againſt this Danger. Yet it went ſo ſlowly on, and with ſo much Caution, that at the <hi>Trojan</hi> Wars Seven hundred Years at leaſt after <hi>Abraham,</hi> we have the Catalogue of a great number of Kings in that little ſpot of Ground which made up <hi>Greece;</hi> all which were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted and engaged in that War, which laſted ſo long, becauſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:110173:5"/>the Kings were many. In <hi>Egypt</hi> the Monarchy was grown to a more Man-like Stature, as appears from the Holy Records: And to that Crown the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were at length Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, even in its more Arbitrary and Unreaſonable Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, without any Regiment or Laws of their own, till the times of <hi>Moſes,</hi> who was firſt their Deliverer,
<note place="margin">Deut. 33.5.</note> and then their King. So that here, as I ſaid, me muſt needs date the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal or Riſe of their Government, when all the Families of the Patriarchs were reduced under one Head, and ſubmitted to <hi>Moſes,</hi> as their univerſal Father, Ruler and Judge.</p>
            <p>The other word to be explained is <hi>Counſellors— thy Counſellors as at the beginning— Counſel</hi> is Conſultation, or Conference about ſome End, which being agreed on, it proceeds to examine and debate the moſt likely means to it. A <hi>Counſellor</hi> is he, who being endow'd with a Talent or Ability for this Work, is called upon and required to ſerve in it. For I take it as a word of Office, in its na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Miniſterial, and a Man ought to have a Call before he aſſumes the Stile. Becauſe, tho' he may be capable to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe wholſom Advice, he is no <hi>Counſellor</hi> until this capacity be brought in to act by his Warrant who gives him leave to offer it with freedom. So that as good <hi>Counſel</hi> (for we take the word in the beſt ſenſe here) is deliberation about a good End, and the contrivance of good Means: And as a <hi>Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor</hi> never anſwers this Character but while he purſues thoſe two things without Self-regard in what he propoſes; ſo the Government cannot but be happy where the Relation is ſuch as the Text gives between <hi>Judges</hi> and <hi>Counſellours;</hi> the <hi>one</hi> not venturing to act without previous and ſolid Advice, and the <hi>other</hi> not daring to offer any Advice but what Experience, Conſcience and Honour declare to be ſerviceable to thoſe Ends for which it is demanded.</p>
            <p>And ſuch was the Government of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> For as <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Joſhua</hi> were the firſt Judges of this Kind, ſo the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors</hi> ſignifie <hi>Aaron</hi> and his Succeſſors in the High-Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, by whoſe <hi>Pectoral, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim</hi> and <hi>Thummim,</hi> or ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, God was pleas'd to reveal his Will, and give them
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110173:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>his Advice in arduous and difficult Caſes. And ſtrictly ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the firſt Government among the <hi>Jews</hi> was purely a <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ocracy;</hi> God was their King, and <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties, the former in <hi>Civil,</hi> the laſt in <hi>Religious</hi> Matters, ſo early, ſo ſacred and relative was the Inſtitution of the <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>Mitre.</hi> And if the Precedence is given the Firſt, it is becauſe the Church is within the State; and Men as they make a Civil Body, are the Matter of all Government here, and their Actions what the Laws are converſant about; ſo that He that is the Head of ſuch a Body, ought to be preferr'd, and bear the Rule, for the preſent conveniency and welfare of the Community. However, the others, as they alſo were the Miniſters of God, they were enabled to aſſiſt by their <hi>Counſel</hi> the Chief Magiſtrate; who for want of their Advice, ſometimes miſcarried in their Affairs, as in the Inſtances of <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s haſty League with the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Targum Jonath.</hi> on Judges 11.39.</note> and <hi>Jeptha</hi>'s dealing with his Daughter.</p>
            <p>To theſe frequently were added <hi>Prophets</hi> Extraordinary, who reported the Divine Pleaſure in the moſt weighty Matters; and <add>ſo</add> this Prophecy of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> was fulfilled in <hi>Ezra, Nehemiah, Hag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gai</hi> and <hi>Zachary.</hi> But the Standing Commiſſion was that of the High-Prieſt, and it was his Office to be a <hi>Counſellor,</hi> as the Office of a Prince to be a <hi>Judge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Under the Kings afterwards there were ſeveral others ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured with the ſame Stile;
<note place="margin">1 Chr. 27. 2 Chr. 10.</note> as <hi>Jonathan</hi> and <hi>Huſhai</hi> were <hi>Counſellours</hi> to <hi>David,</hi> the Old Men to King <hi>Solomon,</hi> and others; and the Miniſtry of theſe may be ſerviceable to the State, where care is taken not to depend too much on the Advice of <hi>Achitophel,</hi> and that <hi>Rehoboam</hi>'s Novices prevail not too much on the Prince's Ambition or Eaſineſs, to Enſlave and Oppreſs the People. And thus for the Firſt thing the Conſtitution referred to— <hi>I will reſtore thy Judges as at the firſt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Before I proceed to my Second Point, it concerns me to ſee, Whether the Notion of the <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> doth not contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict the Interpretation I have made on theſe words. For if they are the <hi>Judges</hi> and <hi>Counſellours</hi> here intended, as ſome
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:110173:6"/>are apt to think, and of ſo great Figure as to Eclipſe the Majeſty of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Princes to that degree, as to let them have no Influence or Authority, but what they claim'd as their Members, or within their number, then I have miſtaken the Meaning of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> and the Nature of the ancient Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> in the return of which, the Prophet fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tells their Happineſs: And which, as I have dated under the the Reigns of <hi>Moſes, Joſhua</hi> and the <hi>Judges,</hi> ſo I underſtand it to be a Compleat Monarchy, with as much Power or more than the Kings after them.</p>
            <p>By the <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> I mean the Senate of Seventy Two,
<note place="margin">So many ſtood up to have the K. Sentenced.</note> (a fatal Number to our late Monarch) being Six out of every Tribe indifferently choſen, to whom ſome <hi>Rabbins,</hi> and others on their Credit, have given ſuch an Exorbitant Power, as not only to affirm, That a King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> could do nothing without them; but aſſert further, that they might <hi>de jure</hi> Cite, Judge and Whip him, as they ſaw reaſon for it. And probably it had been ſo in King <hi>David</hi>'s time, if <hi>Achitophel</hi>'s Succeſs had been equal to his Wiſhes, whom they make the Preſident of ſuch a <hi>Sanhedrim.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The truth is, ſeveral of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Writers, out of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice to the <hi>Roman</hi> and other Monarchies under which they frequently groaned, have ſpoke big Words about the Syne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drial Authority in the Ages of their Fathers: But as they are wanting in the ſolid Proofs and Examples of that Power they ever and anon attribute to it, ſo their Diſcretion may be que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion'd to ſuggeſt ſuch a method of Government to be of Divine Appointment, as might be dangerous to thoſe Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Princes in whoſe Cities and by whoſe Indulgence many of 'em flouriſh and live.</p>
            <p>But we depend not on this Argument; for we ſay, they are injurious to Truth, as well as to their own and thoſe Princes Intereſt: And whatever countenance ſuch a Form may have in other Countries, they have little reaſon to charge their own with it, much leſs make God the Contriver and Founder.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:110173:7"/>
            <p>It muſt be confeſs'd,
<note place="margin">Exod. 18.21.</note> That <hi>Jethro</hi> perſwaded his Son-in-Law <hi>Moſes</hi> to ſubſtitute ſome other <hi>Judges</hi> to hear inferiour Cauſes;
<note place="margin">Numb. 11.16.</note> which he accordingly did, and God was pleas'd to approve and confirm the Deſign. But the Reaſon of it is expreſly ſet down in Scripture and <hi>Joſephus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Antiq. l. 3. c. 3.</note> not in the leaſt to leſſen <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Authority, but to give him ſome eaſe in the execution of Juſtice, and lighten the <hi>Burden,</hi> as both the Writers call it. It was morally impoſſible for <hi>Moſes</hi> in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to go through ſo many Controverſies and Diſputes as daily came before him; ſo that it was neceſſary to appoint theſe Deputies to aſſiſt him in the more trivial Suits, though what they did may be reckon'd his Acts, becauſe done in a Subordinate way, and by Commiſſion from Him.</p>
            <p>That this was ſo, cannot be well doubted, if we conſider that Paſſage which afterwards fell out concerning <hi>Korah,
<note place="margin">Numb. 16.</note> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> and <hi>Abiram.</hi> It appears by this Conſpiracy, that after the Election of the Seventy Elders, <hi>Moſes</hi> had the Sovereign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in his own hands, becauſe their Charge againſt him was, that <hi>He had made himſelf altogether a Prince over them</hi>—and they tell him and <hi>Aaron,
<note place="margin">V. 13.</note> You take too much upon you, and have lifted up your ſelves above the Congregation of the Lord</hi>— An Article that affected them no more than the reſt of the <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hedrim,</hi> had <hi>Korah</hi> and his Fellows then diſcover'd any ſuch mighty Conſiſtory to partake of the Government in which it ſeems <hi>Moſes</hi> would not admit an Equal. What the Iſſue of this Rebellion was, that Chapter ſhews: One Schiſm was puniſh'd with another, and the Earth divided and ſwallowed them up. So that, how Arbitrary ſoever <hi>Moſes</hi> was thought to be, yet it pleas'd God to juſtifie him with Miracle, and by a Plague immediately following, let the People know whom they were to Obey as their Lord and Sovereign.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joſephus</hi> indeed informs us, That under <hi>Moſes</hi> and his Diſciple <hi>Joſhua,</hi> who at that time had the Empire and Army, the Nobility and other Worthy Men Ruled the State.
<note place="margin">Antiq. l. 6. c. 6.</note> He means the One Office was Military the Other Civil; and ſo he ſpeaks, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>He was their General.</hi> Yet in this Caſe, if the Nobility and Elders govern'd independant of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:110173:7"/>the Prince, how could this Author ſay, that after <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s death, the People were without Government eighteen Years, till they found a Valiant Juſt Man to Rule, who with his Succeſſors were call'd <hi>Judges.</hi> This proves their Power to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe with the Prince, or otherwiſe the Nation could not be ſo many Years in an Anarchy or without any Government at all. Nor had there been occaſion to demand of <hi>Phineas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> to whoſe Charge the Adminiſtration of Publick Affairs ſhould be committed, if that Senate had the Power pretended, and could without any other Governour Protect and Rule the Nation.</p>
            <p>We often read in the Book of <hi>Judges,</hi> what a licentious and lawleſs Life the People lead, during the ſeveral <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regnums</hi> or ſpaces of Time between the Death of one <hi>Judge</hi> and the Choice of another: Not that they wanted Laws, but there was not ſufficient Power to force Obedience to them. Thus it is ſaid, that <hi>it came to paſs when the Judge was dead,
<note place="margin">Ch. 2.9.</note> that they returned and corrupted themſelves more than their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in following other Gods, to ſerve them, and bow down to them, they ceaſed not from their own doings,
<note place="margin">Ch. 17.6.</note> nor from their ſtubborn way</hi>— And again— <hi>In thoſe days there was no King in</hi> Iſrael, <hi>but every man did that which was right in his own eyes</hi>— This was too fully explain'd in the Sodomy of <hi>Gibeah,</hi> and <hi>Micah</hi>'s Idolatry in the very Verſe before; which being the proper Subject for the <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> to work upon, as their Republicans give out, and ſeems to be confirmed by that Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Luk. 13.33.</note> that <hi>it could not be that a Prophet ſhould periſh out of</hi> Jeruſalem— the caſe of falſe Doctrine and falſe Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip being the Points, that Court more eſpecially, took cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance of.) If there had been, I ſay, all along from <hi>Moſes</hi> down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, ſuch a ſtanding Authority among the <hi>Jews,</hi> how comes it to paſs, we find the Accounts of ſo much Irreligion and bad Morals in their days, ſo inconſiſtent with the Notion of that Conſiſtory, and the Influence it is ſuppoſed to have had over Prince and People.</p>
            <p>The great Inſtances of Prerogative and Majeſty in making War, creating Judges, and, which we might think the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:110173:8"/>work of the <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> the ordering of Church-Affairs, depoſing ill Miniſters, and the like; That all this was done ſometimes immediately by the Kings themſelves, muſt be evident to any body who will be at the pains to go thro' the Hiſtory of thoſe Princes in the Books of <hi>Samuel, Kings</hi> and <hi>Chronicles.</hi> Nay, the very putting a Prophet to death, or diſcharging him out of Priſon, This alſo was the King's Act, as we ſee in the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Zedekiah</hi> and <hi>Jeremiah;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jerem. 38.</note> and this without the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke or Murmur of that Aſſembly, tho' then the King's Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances were very low, and might have encouraged them to it.</p>
            <p>And when we further add, That the Holy Book charges the King with the execution of Juſtice, and puniſhes him for the Peoples Sins (which would be very hard, if the Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adminiſtration or Miſmanagement were not his own, or that he had not ſufficient Power to order things better.) All this is evidence, That the terrible Notion of the <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> is ſuch a Dream, as perhaps may frighten him that hath it, but is of no great Effect to move other People, or engage them to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it any thing elſe but the diſorder and weakneſs of the ſleeper's Brain.</p>
            <p>Yet we muſt allow, that in the laſt Ages of the <hi>Jews,</hi> after the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Capitivity, this Court made ſome ſmall Figure in that part of the World; and we have a ſad Teſtimony of it in their Behaviour towards the Lord Chriſt; an unparalell'd piece of Barbariſm and Cruelty; ſerviceable indeed to the Decrees of God, and the Redemption of Mankind; but, which ſhews them to be Men without the common Principles of Conſcience and Honeſty, in murdering a Juſt Perſon, whom the Preſident himſelf declared Innocent. But admit them ſuch a Court in thoſe days, with that Plenary Power they boaſt of (which is difficult to prove, and 'tis plain the <hi>Roman</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties were at length above it) yet 'tis a good Anſwer for us to ſay, that <hi>from the beginning it was not ſo</hi>— and we are now ſpeaking of ſuch <hi>Judges as</hi> were <hi>at the firſt,</hi> and ſuch <hi>Counſellours as</hi> were <hi>at the beginning</hi> And though we ſhould admit the Inſtitution of the Seventy Two under the Character
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:110173:8"/>of the latter (as probably ſome of them might be <hi>Counſellours</hi> and Miniſters of State; and therefore <hi>Hebrew</hi> Writers ſay, That it was one neceſſary qualification to recommend them, if they underſtood the Languages, in order to be Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters to their Princes) yet that they were not ſuch <hi>Judges,</hi> as the firſt word ſuppoſes, and had no Power paramount to the Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> appears by what hath been offer'd againſt this Objection. And therefore taking it for granted that the Jewiſh Government was, as indeed it was, <hi>Monarchial,</hi> we paſs to the Second Thing: To ſhew and deſcribe the Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs this People were to have in the <hi>Reſtauration</hi> of that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Conſtitution.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>I will reſtore</hi>— The Government referred to, being that of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron, Joſhua</hi> and the <hi>Judges,</hi> 'twill be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to lay before you, in little, the Acts, Conduct and Behaviour of thoſe Princes, and let you ſee how they did contribute to the Proſperity of their Subjects: And to begin with <hi>Moſes.</hi> His firſt care was to make good Laws, Civil and Religious, and ſee them impartially executed. And what pains he took this way, we may partly read <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.13, &amp;c.— <hi>And</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes <hi>ſate to judge the people, and the people ſtood by</hi> Moſes <hi>from morning unto the evening, and he made them know the Statutes of God and his Laws</hi>— And this he did with ſo much Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, that his Health was in great danger by it; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Raguel</hi> his Wife's Father, gave him the Advice above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mention'd, to appoint Commiſſioners for the deciſion of leſſer Matters.</p>
            <p>When at any time the Neceſſities of the People made them murmur in the Wilderneſs, and gave 'em reaſon, as they thought, to Libel his Government; tho' there was not the leaſt ſhadow of ill Conduct on his ſide, yet his Meekneſs was ſuch, that he would not puniſh the Inſolence, but remembring that their wants extorted it from them, he not only forgave, but pitied and imploy'd the Intereſt he had with God, both to pardon and ſupply them. And his concern for them and their Welfare was ſo remarkable, that when God was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vok'd to that degree, as to reſolve to deſtroy them for their
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:110173:9"/>Idolatry in his abſence, hear what the good Prince ſaith; <hi>Oh this people have ſinned a great ſin,
<note place="margin">Exod. 32.32.</note> and have made them Gods of gold, yet now if thou wilt, forgive their ſin, and if not, blot me, I pray thee, out of the Book which thou haſt written</hi>— ſuch a ſenſe he had of their danger; ſo much a <hi>Father</hi> he was ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than a <hi>King:
<note place="margin">Antiq. l. 4. ad ſin.</note> A Perſon wiſe in his Counſels, and in the Execution of them never had his equal: His Affections ſo much ſubmitted to his Wiſdom, that he ſeem'd not to have any, and that he knew only the names of thoſe Paſſions which he perceived to be active in other men</hi>— So <hi>Joſephus</hi> of him.</p>
            <p>And as for his Diſciple and Succeſſour <hi>Joſhua,</hi> what a Prince he was, appears in that ſhort Character given of him by the ſame Author; <hi>A Man exact in all ſorts of Vertue, incomparably Skilful in matters of Government, Valiant in War, and Wiſe in Peace</hi>—</p>
            <p>And let this be the ſumm of thoſe two Reigns; That they brought the <hi>Jews</hi> from the utmoſt degree of Streights and Slavery, to an admirable height of Riches and Glory; And all this without any benefit to themſelves, beſides the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Honour of having Governed well. This was all the Harveſt they reaped from ſo many Victories; This was the Reward of ſo much Sweat and Blood; This the End of their Watchings and Cares; This the Portion of all the Territories, Subſtance and Treaſures taken from the Enemies: All which they divided among the Tribes, and did it by <hi>Lot,</hi> to avoid the ſuſpicion of gratifying Favourites, or ſetting any mark of diſtinction on their natural or immediate Families. No, all the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were equally their Subjects and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; all to be well provided for; all to be made Happy; all to have a like ſhare in the Succeſs, that as far as in <hi>them</hi> lay, there might be no reaſon for them to envy and curſe one another.</p>
            <p>After <hi>theſe</hi> followed <hi>Othinel, Ehud, Shamgar, Debora</hi> and <hi>Gideon,</hi> who as in deſperate Caſes, they were invited to take the Government on them, ſo they diſcharged the Truſt as Men commiſſion'd from Heaven; <hi>The Spirit of God came up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and they judged</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and the Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpered under them</hi>— Men ſo void of Ambition, that as they
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:110173:9"/>never attempted the Rule before the Dangers of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, the Fears and Addreſſes of the People urged them to it, and God commanded it: So when the Service was over (without any Self-denying Ordinance of their <hi>Sanhedrim</hi>) like the worthy <hi>Roman,</hi> who made good <hi>Iſaiah</hi>'s Prophecy, by turning his <hi>Sword to the Plow-ſhare</hi>) they could have been willing, had it been permitted, to retire to their private life, and Ruled as Kings no longer. And of this <hi>Gideon</hi> is a Proof; who having ſo much obliged the Nation by the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance he had given them from the Hand of <hi>Midian,</hi> that thereupon they propoſed <hi>an Act of Settlement</hi> to ſix the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy in him and his Line, he refuſed and hindred it: So little mixture of Selfiſhneſs there was in all he did, and ſo little would he better himſelf by the help he gave the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed People, or let his Generoſity ask a Crown of 'em. <hi>I will not rule over you, neither ſhall my Son rule over you,
<note place="margin">Judges 8.23.</note> the Lord ſhall rule over you</hi>— And tho' <hi>Joſephus</hi> tells us, that he did <hi>Rule the</hi> Iſraelites <hi>for the ſpace of forty Years;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Antiq. l. 5. c. 8.</note> yet he ſaith withal, that <hi>he laboured to be diſmiſs'd the Government, but was conſtrained to continue in it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will name but one more, and he was the laſt of them, I mean <hi>Samuel,</hi> whoſe Government was ſo eaſie all his time, that he makes this Challenge: <hi>Behold,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>here I am,
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 12.3.</note> witneſs againſt me before the Lord; whoſe Oxe have I taken, or whom have I defrauded? Whom have I oppreſſed? or of whoſe hand have I receive any bribe? And they ſaid,
<note place="margin">— 4.</note> Thou haſt not defrauded us, nor oppreſſed us, neither haſt thou taken ought of any mans hand</hi>— So little had he vexed or burden'd them du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his Government, but followed thoſe excellent Patterns ſet before him.</p>
            <p>And if the <hi>Judges</hi> were ſuch, we need not fear but the <hi>Counſellours</hi> were like them. Either ſuch Men, whoſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples lead them to advance the Publick Good, or whoſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion would not offer at any other Advice than what was agreeable to the Sovereign's Mind, who always ſtudied and deſired nothing more than the Honour and Safety of the Nation.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:110173:10"/>
            <p>So that the reſult is this: If it be a good Conſtitution where a Nation flouriſhes; where its Territories are inlarged; where the Subjects are made rich and formidable; where the People are ſecured from Oppreſſion at home, and from being a prey to Enemies abroad, put out all fear of being enſlaved by their own Prince or any Foreigner, then the Government of <hi>Iſrael</hi> we have been hitherto deſcribing, deſerves that Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter; and we have reaſon enough to believe, the Prophet pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed the <hi>Jews</hi> a Bleſſing in the Text, where he ſpeaks of a <hi>Reſtauration,</hi> and that God would give them ſuch <hi>Judges</hi> as they had <hi>at firſt,</hi> and ſuch <hi>Counſellours</hi> as they had in <hi>the beginning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus I have done with the Two things I propoſed for the Heads of my Diſcourſe: The <hi>Original Conſtitution</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the <hi>Happineſs</hi> of being <hi>reſtored</hi> to it.</p>
            <p>But what is this to us? The <hi>Civil Politie</hi> of that People concern us no more than their <hi>Eccleſiaſtical:</hi> Both were Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, and we have ſeen their period. And unleſs we had ſecurity that all Sovereign Princes would be as Faithful as <hi>Moſes,</hi> as Pious as <hi>David,</hi> or were as Wiſe or Peaceable as <hi>Solomon,</hi> unbiaſs'd by any Motives but what adminiſtred to the Proſperity of a Nation committed to their charge, we have no cogent Reaſon to take this Precedent, and to make our ſelves Slaves to one Man's Pride and Ambition. The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of ſuch a <hi>Ruler Samuel</hi> gives— 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11, to 19— and 'twill be ſome labour to ſanctifie it into a Bleſſing.</p>
            <p>Thus, or to this purpoſe, they argue againſt the beſt of Governments: But to ſay ſomewhat to the Objections.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, the Government of <hi>Judea</hi> obliges not to an Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; yet I think it may be ſafely ſaid to redound much to the Credit of <hi>Monarchy,</hi> that the wiſe God himſelf was pleas'd to begin it among his Favourite-people; and that Nature taught, and Hiſtories ſhew it to be every where the only Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment for above half the Age of the World after the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation. And tho' indeed in progreſs of time ſome <hi>Republicks</hi> intruded into <hi>Greece</hi> and other Places, yet it is obſervable, that our great Redeemer the Lord Chriſt, ſeems to <hi>reſtore</hi> it at the <hi>Incarnation,</hi> when there was nothing beſides <hi>Monarchy</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:110173:10"/>over the whole Univerſe. And it ſuffices that <hi>They</hi> admit the <hi>Conſtitution</hi> good, <hi>if the Men,</hi> ſet to Govern, were ſuitable to it.</p>
            <p>But, alas, <hi>Princes</hi> are ſubject to <hi>Appetites, Inſirmities</hi> and <hi>Paſſions.</hi> And it is not to be denied, for all this is humane Nature; There is no <hi>Theocracy</hi> now: <hi>Princes</hi> are <hi>Men,</hi> and not <hi>Gods,</hi> and where are Men without Paſſions?</p>
            <p>By the Influence of theſe therefore they may be tempted to Tyranny. Nor is it unlikely, for we ſometimes read of ſuch a Tyrant over many Cities, and it was ſad for the Subject; But we read alſo of 30 Tyrants in one City, which was worſe, and it was a glorious Act in <hi>Thraſybulus</hi> to expel 'em.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Princes</hi> are Ambitious, and the greedineſs of their Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites intolerable. But is it not the ſame Caſe under other Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments, call them what you will? Every Senatour hath his Ambition and his Favourites too. And ſurely the Charge muſt be ſo much the more to feed and inrich ſo many. And where the Governours ſwell to a great number, in proportion the Expence and Burden muſt be greater.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Kings</hi> are Touchy, and <hi>their Wrath like the roaring of a Lion</hi>— And as they have Power, ſo they cannot long want opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities to exert that Power; and their Revenge is ſure and heavy. But then theſe dreadful Reſentments reach very few in compariſon of thoſe Places where the Rulers abound, and where it is almoſt impoſſible for a Subject to eſcape, when there are ſo many Eyes to ſee Faults, and ſo many Hands to puniſh them.</p>
            <p>And of this the State of <hi>Venice</hi> is a ſad Example, where even the better ſort of Citizens muſt reſolve either to flee abroad, or be ruined at home, upon the leaſt offence given a Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, or any in his Train; and ſometimes perhaps, when there is no other proof but bare ſuggeſtion to make the Sufferer guilty. And in general, it is the common Obſervation of Travellers abroad, that they ſeldom read <hi>Liberty</hi> writ over the Gate, but entring the City they find <hi>Slavery</hi> within.</p>
            <p>Yet the unthinking People ſwallow the Bait, and are greedy of the Purchaſe, tho' they pay never ſo dear for it. Such is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:110173:11"/>the itch of Ambition and Gain, which tho' Objects at a vaſt diſtance, yet they all hope in time to reach them; and then the uſe they put 'em to, is the very ſame with what Men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign by the <hi>other Commiſſions</hi> they take, which is not for the ſake of the <hi>common Good,</hi> but in order to make up a <hi>broken Fortune.</hi> And in the mean while, they bear the Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens laid upon them in expectation of their own turns, to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs their Fellow-Citizens, or Country-men; the proſpect of which is the ſole comfort theſe miſerable wretches have to buoy 'em up under the weight of their own Oppreſſions and Bondage.</p>
            <p>This is indeed more properly in <hi>Popular</hi> Governments; yet in <hi>Oligarchy</hi> the Motive hath its place from the like <hi>Rota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> or <hi>Circle</hi> of Succeſſion in all the beneficial Imployments of the <hi>State,</hi> which is confeſſedly the riſe of particular Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies; but how the Commonwealth ſuffers by it, is eaſily ſeen, when we may diſcover in the Accounts, that beſides the neceſſary Expences of the <hi>Publick</hi> in <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>War,</hi> vaſt Treaſures are conſumed to ſatisfie private appetites, and make 'em amends for their patience ſo long.</p>
            <p>But over and above that Inconvenience, what dangerous Conſequences this <hi>Courſe</hi> hath, we may be able to gueſs, by remembring the Caſe of <hi>Alcibiades</hi> at <hi>Athens,</hi> and ſome other Captains at <hi>Rome,</hi> who by the Cuſtom of their <hi>Rotation</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing laid aſide, and their Commiſſions given to unexperienc'd Men, the Fleet of the <hi>firſt</hi> and the Army of the <hi>laſt,</hi> were brought to great extremities, and at length utterly loſt, by an unſeaſonable Compliance with the Suffrages of the People. 'Tis true, ſometimes their Fears taught 'em more Wiſdom, and they thought fit to overlook this Cuſtom in the frequent Conſulſhips of <hi>Marius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 18.40.</note> &amp;c. But for the moſt part their Temper was that of the Multitude, who were obſtinate in their choice of <hi>Barrabbas</hi> before <hi>Jeſus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 19.32.</note> Or elſe all in hurly-burly, like them at <hi>Epheſus— Some cried one thing, and ſome another; for the Aſſembly was confuſed, and the moſt part knew not wherefore they were come together</hi>—</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:110173:11"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Some cry one thing, and ſome another</hi>—That's another Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune all theſe ſorts of Governments are liable to. For E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulations, Jealouſies and Envyings, are natural to Men of equal Power. And from hence ariſe <hi>Factions</hi> and <hi>Parties,</hi> who in all their Debates, do not ſo much weigh <hi>what</hi> is ſaid, as <hi>who</hi> it was that ſaid it; and the Counſel is good or bad; not as it concerns the Publick, but as it ſuits their Affections and Intereſt, whoſe <hi>Induſtry</hi> can produce <hi>majority of Votes,</hi> and whoſe great <hi>Reaſon</hi> is <hi>Number.</hi> This very thing was fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal to <hi>Carthage,</hi> one of the mighty'ſt Commonwealths the Sun ever ſhin'd on; when the Malice of <hi>Hanno</hi>'s Faction ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd againſt <hi>Hannibal,</hi> as to force him back from <hi>Italy</hi> for want of Supplies, chuſing rather to ſink their own City, than let that brave Captain Subdue <hi>Rome</hi> to it. As it accordingly fell out, the Enemy following their Conqueror home, and in the iſſue deſtroying <hi>Carthage</hi> and him.</p>
            <p>Theſe are Miſchiefs a Monarch is not ſo much expos'd to: And tho' he hath <hi>many,</hi> and probably <hi>different, Counſels</hi> offer'd him, yet ſtill they are no more than <hi>Counſels,</hi> which the Prince may take or let alone. <hi>Adviſers</hi> may claſh and hate one another; but the Governour being <hi>one,</hi> if he cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile <hi>them,</hi> he can reconcile <hi>what</hi> they propoſe to the Publick good, at leaſt ſo much of it as will ſerve his preſent turn, without ſcaring their reſentments who are of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Opinion, and <hi>who are Counſellors, and not Dictators,</hi> as the <hi>Royal Martyr</hi> makes the Expreſſion.</p>
            <p>I ſpeak all this in purſuance of my Subject, and to ſhew in ſome low degree, That the Exceptions againſt <hi>Monarchy</hi> are in reality, but ſo many Props to ſupport it.</p>
            <p>The great Proof of <hi>Divine Right</hi> I have not touch'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor will any further mention it, then in the <hi>Monarchy</hi> of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> which being of God's appointment, it may ſpeak for it ſelf, tho' not in the language of an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Law</hi> to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blige every where to an Imitation. I acknowledge <hi>Magiſtracy,</hi> with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> to be <hi>an Ordinance of Heaven,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note> and the Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of it Sacred. But for the <hi>Model,</hi> I mean what <hi>Form</hi> to expreſs it in, I leave that to humane Prudence, and conſider
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:110173:12"/>it with St. <hi>Peter,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.13.</note> the Creature of Man.</hi> And as it is made for the good of Men, who are the Matter of Government, ſo 'tis left to Men to digeſt it to their conveniency, and make it anſwer the end of its Inſtitution. And therefore a Subject at <hi>Venice, Genoa</hi> or <hi>Holland,</hi> is under the ſame obligation of Obedience with him in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> and he is to <hi>ſubmit not only for Wrath, but Conſcience-ſake.</hi> If he <hi>reſiſts</hi> in any of thoſe places, <hi>he reſiſts the Ordinance of God; and they that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, ſhall receive to themſelves damnation</hi>—</p>
            <p>But as to what concerns our ſelves, we have that <hi>Form</hi> and that <hi>Happineſs</hi> the Text ſpeaks of; and the Argument for it is the Prophet's, <hi>Original Conſtitution,</hi> having our <hi>Judges as at the firſt, and our Counſellors as at the beginning.</hi> So that Preſcription gives it the right, and 'tis the <hi>Bleſſing of the Day</hi> to have it <hi>reſtored,</hi> and be put in the poſſeſſion of it again.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>— was the wholeſom Advice of the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Nice</hi> to compoſe the Church of God.
<note place="margin">Conc. Ni-Cen. Can. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Cuſtom</hi> is a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid Plea; a thing for the moſt part very Venerable and Sacred, or at leaſt eſteemed ſo. We ſee the force of it in very trivial Inſtances, I will not ſay ſeemingly Ridiculous; tho' poſſibly were our Fathers alive to give the reaſon of 'em, we might diſcover 'em to be the Fruits of good Contrivance and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and as fooliſh as they appear, it might be in many caſes more folly to reject 'em.</p>
            <p>We hold our <hi>Monarchy</hi> by this Tenure; and whether we take our ſelves for <hi>Aborigines</hi> or <hi>Cadmean</hi> born; whether deſcended from <hi>Phaenicia</hi> or <hi>Troy, Rome</hi> or <hi>Germany,</hi> or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever other birth the Hiſtories or Fancies of Men give us; whether <hi>Saxons, Danes, Normans</hi> or <hi>Scots;</hi> whether before, under, or after the <hi>Heptarchy;</hi> whether of the Line of <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſter</hi> or <hi>York;</hi> whether before or after the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of this Iſland into the one Name of <hi>Great Britain;</hi> Fix us where you will, we can find nothing but <hi>Monarchy</hi> among us, with thoſe Helps and Aſſiſtants of it the Text mentions and we now enjoy; and tho' we loſe our ſelves in point of Pedegree, yet the Evidence of this Government is ſo clear and ſtrong, that I may honeſtly apply what <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith, That <hi>our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:110173:12"/>are as at the firſt, and our Counſellors as at the beginning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I confeſs our late unhappy Times have left a Proof of the Uncertainty of <hi>Humane Affairs,</hi> and told us, That there is nothing ſo <hi>Ancient,</hi> or ſo <hi>well Setled,</hi> but what is expos'd to Change and Violence. But to be ſilent in the <hi>Novelty</hi> of ſuch a bold Attempt to diſturb the Throne, and Out Him who had it in poſſeſſion, what were the Effects of this <hi>Reformation? What were the fruits of thoſe things whereof we are now aſhamed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Monarchy</hi> expiring, in how many Shapes, by a kind of a <hi>Pythagorean</hi> Conveyance, was the Government ſeen; and after that Doctrine, ſuited to the Nature of the Animal it appear'd in: Sometimes a Body with many Heads, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times with none; and, which was Unnatural too, one while <hi>the Eye would ſay to the Hand, I have no need of thee; and the Head to the Feet, I have no need of you.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.21, 23.</note> And herein a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone they cloſed with St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Alluſion, That <hi>thoſe Members of the Body</hi> which were <hi>leſs honourable, upon theſe they beſtow'd more abundant Honour, and the uncomely parts had more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant comelineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt Innovation was, to Vote the <hi>Biſhops</hi> an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeleſs,</hi> nay <hi>Dangerous</hi> part of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper Houſe:</hi> And not long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, all the <hi>Lords</hi> became as <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeleſs</hi> and <hi>Dangerous</hi> as <hi>they.</hi> Nor did the <hi>Lower Houſe</hi> ſtop here, for they were not pleas'd with their own <hi>Members,</hi> but <hi>Secluded</hi> many of them; and after a while were <hi>all</hi> of 'em requited <hi>in Specie,</hi> and ſent home as <hi>a pack of Men</hi> (ſo it was told 'em) <hi>who had arrogated to themſelves, their Friends and Dependants, all the Honours, Commands, and gainful Imployments of the Kingdom.</hi> This was done by the <hi>Army;</hi> and 'twas fair enough the Wheel ſhould move on; and ſince what the <hi>Parliament</hi> did was by their Swords, it was highly reaſonable that in their turns they ſhould have ſome ſhare in the common Prey. And as their <hi>Mace</hi> outweigh'd the <hi>Scepter,</hi> ſo the <hi>Sword</hi> had the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of being ſharper; and their <hi>Darling</hi> at length could not endure that the <hi>Fools Bauble,</hi> as he call'd the Speaker's
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:110173:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>Mace ſhould pretend to ſtand in Competition with it. This was a ſure Teſtimony of the Divine Vengeance, to pay 'em in their own Coin, and let their <hi>Slaves</hi> ſerve them, as they had ſerved their Sovereign <hi>Maſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now at laſt we are come to the ſad Objection againſt <hi>Monarchy,</hi> I mean <hi>Deſpotick</hi> or <hi>Abſolute</hi> Power, when the <hi>Will</hi> is <hi>Law,</hi> and the <hi>Sword Executioner.</hi> An Event not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending on Imagination and Fancy; but what was our real Condition, and how many were forced to weep it in Tears and Blood? The common Complaints were, <hi>Sequeſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Free-quarter, Sacrilege, Conſiſcations, Impriſonments, Executions,</hi> and other Inſtances of <hi>Oppreſſion,</hi> as num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berleſs as their ways of Government, their <hi>Council of State, Council of War, High Courts of Juſtice, Protectorſhip, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Safety, Rump</hi> or <hi>Junto,</hi> with other Forms under o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Names. What could be expected from this variety of Intereſts, but that the Nation muſt ſuffer to gratifie their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Affections and Deſires? And how could it be thought, that an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper</hi> ſhould thruſt himſelf into Power, and not be a <hi>Tyrant</hi> to be able to maintain it? And where can Tyranny be but Miſery will follow? And, <q>
                  <hi>What was both the reproach and aggravation of this Miſery; thoſe Flies that ſucked us, were but the offspring of Dirt and Dunghils. Our Plague was like that of</hi> Egypt, <hi>the very Duſt of the Earth crawled upon us. The meaneſt of the People were our Rulers, and out of thoſe Brambles proceeded a Fire that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed the Cedars of</hi> Lebanon.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus as to the <hi>State;</hi> and for the <hi>Church</hi> it was rent in pieces by manifold Errors, Schiſms and Hereſies; not only tolerated, but embraced, defended and impoſed, to ſink our Conſciences as low as our Fortunes, and make our Condition every way deplorable.
<note place="margin">Catalogus Errorum, Hareſium &amp; Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miarum in Anglia ab Ann, 1640. <hi>Arndii Lex.</hi>
               </note> I bluſh to think of the Number. But a Foreigner has publiſh'd it. <hi>A Catalogue of Errors, Hereſies and Blaſphemies in</hi> England, 1640—He reckons up no leſs then one hundred and fourſcore <hi>Heterodoxies</hi> in thoſe days, when Holineſs walk'd the Streets with ſo much noiſe, and the Reformers made a ſhew of making a glorious Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:110173:13"/>as indeed they did, the ſame way as they made the Defender of it a <hi>Glorious King,</hi> by ſending both to Heaven. I am ſorry a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> ſhould have any juſt Reaſon to write this Account; and that a <hi>Papiſt</hi> ſhould be able to argue from it, to diſgrace the beſt conſtituted Church on the face of the Earth, which was then under a ſevere Perſecution, and gave no colour for any uncharitable Reflection.</p>
            <p>But I take no delight in rubbing theſe Sores, which the Clemency of the Government would heal for the future. And I am ſo far from Malice, or revenging theſe Wrongs, that I read of <hi>Thraſybulus</hi>'s <hi>Amneſty</hi> at <hi>Athens</hi> with high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Satisfaction; and think <hi>David</hi> never did a more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Act, then when he pardon'd <hi>Shimei</hi> at his <hi>Reſtauration</hi> after the Rebellion of <hi>Abſalom.</hi> An <hi>Act of Indemnity</hi> and <hi>Oblivion</hi> is ſomewhat like the Conduct of God, who hath power enough to puniſh all his Enemies, but his Mercy will not let him. Yet as God, ſo may we at the ſame time abhor and mention Sins, when we pity and paſs by the Men who did 'em. And as from them our Calamities came [<hi>A Chaos of Confuſion and Hell of Miſeries,</hi> as the unfortunate King call'd 'em] we may view and point at them, as People after Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wreck do, at a Rock where they miſcarried, by way of <hi>cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to themſelves and others, not to ſplit on that Rock a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. And ſurely I may do here, as in the Devotion and Service of the Day, ſet before our ſelves and God the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Confuſions we were lately under, in order to bleſs him with the greater warmth, by being made ſenſible what it was we were deliver'd from.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Paſſeover</hi> among the <hi>Jews</hi> was an Anniverſary Feſtival appointed by Heaven it ſelf to remember the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, and the Peoples redemption out of it. And their Meals at that time conſiſted of ſuch Ingredients or Meſſes as ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied both; and therefore tho' the <hi>Bread</hi> was <hi>ſweet,</hi> the <hi>Herbs</hi> were <hi>bitter.</hi> So that Neceſſity required to ſay ſomewhat of the Nature and Cauſes of our Troubles, that we might bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reflect on what has been done for us, and be thereupon induced to walk more carefully for the time to come.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:110173:14"/>
            <p>By what hath been ſaid, we learn plainly, that the beſt of Governments is like the moſt uſeful Element of Water; which keeping in its place and common courſe, is pleaſant and ſerviceable to us. It glides gently on without noiſe, or ſuch as pleaſes the Ear, and makes its Murmurs very agreeable. It refreſhes and feeds as it paſſes along, and is neceſſary many ways for Life and Diverſion. But once diverted and turn'd out, of its own Banks, it immediately becomes a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive Flood, and ruſhes forward in a muddy, impetuous Stream. It roars, fumes, rages, drowns and overwhelms all before it: And notwithſtanding in its own Nature, and the Creators Deſign, it was made for manifold uſes; yet now it carries nothing but Miſchief in its current; and, as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſpeaks, it is no other than the <hi>Waters of Strife and Blood,</hi> until it be reduced to its old Channel.</p>
            <p>This Day reports that great Work done which hath made it again <hi>Waters of Comfort.</hi> The remembrance of it calls for Thanks; and that our Thanks may be the more hearty, let me crave your patience for a few words more to repreſent our Condition.</p>
            <p>We have the happieſt <hi>Conſtitution</hi> in the univerſal World. A <hi>Monarchy</hi> not more Ancient than it is Safe. Wherein the <hi>Prince</hi> hath as much <hi>Majeſty</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> as may ſatisfie one who would anſwer the Honour and Character of his Place, to be the Baſis of the <hi>Commonweal,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> a Father of his Country,</hi> and <hi>a Shepherd of his People.</hi> He hath Figure enough to make himſelf both feared and loved. He hath Authority and Opportunities ſufficient to reward or puniſh his Subjects, as by their good or ill Actions they ſhall deſerve it of him. The Intereſt he hath in a brave, rich People, will make him honourable abroad; and he hath many ways to gain our Affections, and cauſe him to be dear to us at home. In a word, he wants nothing to render him Great, but Power and Means to be a <hi>Tyrant;</hi> and that's a Stile doth not, nor will ever ſuit an <hi>Engliſh King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Subjects are Free and Maſters of Property, which the Prince can no more Invade than we his Throne; the ſame
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:110173:14"/>Laws being the King's <hi>Prerogative</hi> and our <hi>Protection.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Privilegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um regis &amp; libertates Angliae.</note> We ſit every Man under his own Vine, and own Fig-tree; and when we part with any proportion of the Fruits, it muſt be with conſent, and by virtue of Laws of our own making.</p>
            <p>And this we owe, as to the good Temper and good Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of our Princes from time to time; ſo alſo to the Vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance and Care of our moſt Auguſt Aſſembly, who have both Wiſdom enough to be ſtiled the <hi>King's Great Council,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Magnum conſilium regis Angl.</note> and ſufficient Authority to be <hi>Patriots</hi> to their Country: And on this account, we do well to comply with the word of the Text, to call 'em <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or, in the language of our Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Commune Conſilium,</hi> becauſe their Advice reaches King and People, and they are the <hi>Copula</hi> and means of that mutual Underſtanding and Affection which ought to be between them.</p>
            <p>Whether the Reign of <hi>Edw.</hi> I. gave 'em the name of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> I anſwer not, but the Thing was in being many Ages before, as appears from King <hi>Sebert</hi> and King <hi>Ina,</hi> by whom they are called <hi>Ancient Sages,</hi> and by their Advice the <hi>laſt</hi> made his excellent Laws, and the <hi>firſt</hi> receiv'd his <hi>Baptiſm</hi> above eleven hundred Years ago. And I believe, upon an induſtrious enquiry, we may advance many Ages further, and there diſcover the grey Hairs of theſe <hi>Aldermen,</hi> as the old Books call 'em.</p>
            <p>Such is the Original State and Temper of our <hi>Engliſh Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy,</hi> where our <hi>Judges</hi> and our <hi>Counſellors</hi> keep together, and jointly endeavour to make the Nation Happy. And if other Deſigns ſhould at any time be in their Heads, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come and are intended for Checks to one another.</p>
            <p>And as we have our <hi>Moſes</hi> and thoſe <hi>Counſellors</hi> in the <hi>State,</hi> ſo we have the other <hi>Counſellor</hi> of the Text, our <hi>Aaron,</hi> in the <hi>Temple;</hi> and in both we would emblem Heaven where the <hi>Great Monarch</hi> ſits, the God of all Power, and the God of our Religion.</p>
            <p>Our Doctrines are pure; our Ceremonies ſignificant and few; and as the <hi>firſt</hi> teaches us to be Good, ſo by the help of the <hi>other</hi> we are able to expreſs it. Our Principles lead
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:110173:15"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:110173:15"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:110173:16"/>us to ſubmit to Government, in order to diſcharge Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and make our ſelves happy under it. And as all the Laws which ſecure a <hi>State</hi> are ſanctified at our Altars, ſo we have a double benefit by our obedience to them; Proſperity here, and Glory in Heaven. Not to Injure another, is the Subſtance of all thoſe Laws: Which, as they tie <hi>our</hi> Hands, ſo they reſtrain the greedy Deſires of <hi>other</hi> People, and thereby we ſecurely enjoy our own. In ſhort, the Sacred Truths recommended to us, are <hi>Holineſs, Sobriety</hi> and <hi>Love;</hi> and the Diſcipline among us is to no other End, than to preſs us to embrace and practiſe them. There is no more <hi>Arbitrary Power</hi> in the <hi>Epiſcopal Chair</hi> then in the <hi>Throne;</hi> yet we have Rules enough to contradict and diſcourage Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſneſs and Anarchy; but ſo well temper'd and ſo well applied with a mixture of <hi>Zeal</hi> and <hi>Prudence,</hi> that there is no danger of an <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> however formed, whether after the Model of <hi>Geneva</hi> or <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This</hi> is our <hi>Government,</hi> and <hi>this</hi> our <hi>Religion,</hi> which, during ſome ill Days, was not only cover'd with <hi>Clouds of Darkneſs,</hi> but moreover loaded with <hi>Tempeſt and Thunder.</hi> But the <hi>Sun of Righteouſneſs</hi> hath been ſtrong enough to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſe them. God in mercy hath removed our Fears, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored Light and a Serene Air again. This Day is the <hi>Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial</hi> of our Deliverance. And as on the <hi>one ſide</hi> we yield God Praiſe for reſcuing us from thoſe great and apparent Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers wherewith we were encompaſſed, ſo on the <hi>other</hi> let us acknowledge it purely his goodneſs that we were not given quite over as a prey unto them; and withal beſeech him ſtill to continue ſuch his Mercies towards us, that all the World may know that he is our <hi>Reſtorer,</hi> our <hi>Saviour</hi> and <hi>Deliverer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to engage him to this, let us further beg, That he wou'd be pleas'd to beſtow upon us ſuch a portion of his Grace, and the aſſiſtance of that <hi>Bleſſed Spirit</hi> (the plentiful effuſion of whoſe manifold Gifts we <hi>now</hi> commemorate) that <hi>being</hi> thus <hi>delivered out of the Hands of our Enemies, we</hi> may make it our buſineſs <hi>to ſerve him without fear in holineſs and righteouſneſs all the days of our life;</hi> and hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:110173:16"/>deſerve to be called, as in the words following my Text, <hi>The City of Righteouſneſs, the Faithful City.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This will ſettle the <hi>Church,</hi> and ſix the <hi>Throne;</hi> confirm our <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Peace;</hi> render us Happy now, and Bleſſed in Eternal Life and Glory above. To which God in his infinite Goodneſs bring us all in his due time, thro' the Interceſſion and Merits of Jeſus Chriſt, to whom with the Father and Holy Ghoſt, be Honour and Glory World without End. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>At St.</hi> Paul<hi>'s</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>May</hi> 29. 1699.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>OF <hi>Publick Baptiſm.</hi> A Sermon preach'd before the Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable the Lord-Mayor, and the Court of Aldermen, at <hi>Guild-Hall-Chapel, Novemb.</hi> 20. 1692. By <hi>Philip Stubs,</hi> M. A. Fellow of <hi>Wadham-College, Oxon.</hi> and Chaplain to the Right Reverend Father in God, <hi>Robert</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter.</hi> The Second Edition, with a <hi>Poſtſcript.</hi> Occaſion'd by a late Conference of the Lord Biſhop's of <hi>London</hi> with his <hi>City Clergy</hi> thereupon. Containing the Concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Judgment of the Moſt Reverend Father in God, Dr. <hi>Tillotſon,</hi> late Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury;</hi> the Right Reverend Dr. <hi>Kidder,</hi> Dr. <hi>Stratford,</hi> Dr. <hi>Gardiner,</hi> Dr. <hi>Williams,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Bath and Wells, Cheſter, Lincoln, Chicheſter,</hi> and others: Earneſtly recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that Catholick Uſage to the Clergy and Laity in their Viſitation Charges, Advices, Sermons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Price 4 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>James Bonwicke,</hi> at the <hi>Hat</hi> and <hi>Star</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
